hello everyone
welcome to cultivating wisdom with john
raviki we're still working with one
camera today
uh jason and amar put in a lot of time
this morning trying to get the two
camera system to work
um still not successful so we're still
working on it we hope to have it fixed
uh by next weekend so as always we will
begin
with um the sit together uh we will
begin with a chant then we'll move into
the silent sit
and we'll come out of it perhaps you'll
recite the five promises to yourself
uh then we'll jason will move the camera
uh we'll move to the whiteboard we'll
continue with the wisdom on hypatia
uh more on stoicism and then we'll come
back to this position
and answer questions you might have so
it's wonderful to be here
um and you guys have the view from above
uh so
which is excellent uh so please get
yourself into position
uh set your phones and do not disturb
we will begin together we'll begin with
chanting when i say begin
[Music]
begin
one
[Music]
[Laughter]
one
[Music]
begin your silence set
so
you
[Music]
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition
character and communitas perhaps by
reciting the five promises to yourself
okay jason's gonna help me move the
camera and let's
move to the dharma
so we're on the second degree of wisdom
in
the western tradition the wisdom of
hypatia we're basically in the high
school and we're talking about stoicism
i hope you're also seeing
retrospectively the continuities
with epicureanism so we've been talking
about some basic principles
one of the first principles is the
internalization of socrates or the
internalization of the sage
for stoicism it's socrates socrates
plays to the western tradition
what the figure like the buddha or lao
say play within the eastern traditions
we're internalizing the sage in order to
transform our inner dialogue remember
anticipates i've learned to converse
with myself
i learned via logos i replace inner
babble
in a monkey mind with inner socratic
dialogue and
imagine what that would be like if that
became our normal way of being
and then that's a and we talked about
the process of
internalization as a perspectival
process
we talked about pygotsky and we did
last time the view from above as a way
of trying to
enact that third-person sage-like
perspective
and then practice internalizing it into
our own perspective
to give us the higher highest order
metacognitive
meta-perspectival ability to reconfigure
what we find salient and relevant in a
way so that we are
constantly tempted by our salience
landscaping
to what is good what is the good life
and that leads us of course to the idea
of aspiration that we are
aspiring uh to become wise
and this is a participatory knowing this
is where we're actually knowing
by living it by loving it by uh
by being bound to it coupled to it so
that
our identity is being transformed as our
way
of knowing it this of course is the only
way you know
virtue you only know honesty by becoming
more and more honest
and you can only know honesty if you
already have some honesty to degree
to some degree and so the idea here is
uh what we're trying to do and becoming
wise is we're trying to seek we're
aspiring to that which is always good
because the stoics ask the question what
is always good
and what is always good is wisdom and
then
he's talked about an idea of wisdom as
deeply connected to the virtue uh virtue
is basically the beauty of wisdom
virtue is how you appropriately discern
what is most relevant and important in
this situation in a way that
most reliably affords you
moving towards the good life
and so uh there's deep connections and
this is
very intrinsic to stoicism between
wisdom and rationality
where rationality doesn't just mean what
we now think of it as sort of formal
logic being more logical avoiding
inconsistency
uh logic that's why i often use the term
for this the stoic
psychologic it has much more to do with
comprehensively overcoming
um self-deception
so what we're actually after is a kind
of self-transcending rationality a
rationality that affords us to become
more rational
that affords us to become more rational
because and this is the
of course you'll see where this will end
up this will end up in the platonic
um ascent out of the cave uh the idea
that as i become less self-deceived i
come to realize the real patterns that
thereby help me to become less
self-deceived
and so on and so forth so when we're
talking about wisdom
we're talking about now that we get
better at judging what is real
that's what for the for the stoics the
core of rationality is not
argumentation um it's
judgment it has to do with our ability
to judge what is real
our ability to desire what is good
and our ability to move to more of an
ability to move towards
to orient to identify with that which is
most
in our control and what's most in our
control of course
is the capacity uh by which we make
meaning so the training of rationality
so before i get into this and we'll
we're going to learn for today the
dharma
i want to address the question some a
series of questions that came up
uh last time in connection with the term
i used i made a distinction it's the
distinction that the
stoics make between emotion
which is to be in motion by the way to
move out
emote right um and passion
and they compare this to walking down a
hill and this is running down here while
you lose control and then some of you
uh for example i think mark made a very
um you know
very well written comment about it
exists because it's but aren't most
things you know
done with passion that can things people
don't acquire
like don't achieve great things they
didn't meant to require achieve great
things
uh unless there's passion
uh so what we're what the problem we're
facing with that is we're
we're facing anachronistic equivocation
uh
where equivocation is two different
meanings of the same term
and anachronism is to not pay attention
to historical context
so let's pay attention to the let's pay
attention first of all to the
go back in the history of this word and
it's deeply related to
this word passive passion is the
opposite of action
when you're passive you're not engaging
you're not acting
um the the stoic term that's being used
here
is um is pathe
it's where we get our term pathetic from
so what the stoics mean by passion
is when we become pathetic because we
are completely passive
in the face of our arousal and our
effective state
it has run away with us and that's the
metaphor of running down
uh the hill now what's really
interesting is
we have taken this term and we've made
uh to be strongly motivated
and and in terms of strongly committed
so
motivated not just i have the impulse
but i'm actually committing myself
which of course is the opposite of being
past passive
uh strongly committed
it's the opposite of being passive it's
the opposite of being pathetic
we hear this term and we hear it as sort
of uh you know
heroism heroism um
now what the stoics would say to that
idea of how that term has gotten so far
away from
its original meaning like the meaning of
the word stoic
like the meaning of the word cynic um is
that it reflects uh a kind of confusion
that and this is what modern stoics say
that's prevalent in our culture
where we tend to confuse we've talked
about this before we talked about the
epicureans we tend to infuse we tend to
confuse intensity
uh with commitment that the only thing
that makes us committed to things
is the experience of intense feeling um
and what the stoics would say to that is
now what you're
actually what you actually need for
commitment
is because feelings are actually not
long-standing
and feelings vacillate um and feelings
contradict themselves one moment you're
feeling uh then the next one you're
feeling this and affiliates don't lie
what they say is what they would ask you
what actually
what actually keeps people in
long-term commitment it's a very good
question
i mean this is a question so let's
compare let's compare the intensity of
infatuation
with the commitment of love if you were
to try
and keep committed to your
partner through always you know trying
to rely
on that in the intensity of infatuation
and of course people do this
uh we call them infatuation junkies and
that picks up on something that mark was
saying he was he was
trying to think about with this more in
terms of addiction
but you know if the infatuation junkie
is somebody
who once the infatuation fades as it
inevitably does
because that is the nature of feeling
the relationship ends
what actually keeps
the relationship going a relationship of
love well it's it's commitment
it's commitment and what is it in a
person
that keeps them committed well things
think of the things you say
you know well they're honest um
they listen they communicate
they're sincere they're willing to adapt
and adjust
they bind their sense of who they are to
the other person
notice what we're not we're not talking
about feelings now what we're talking
about
we're talking about what the stoics
talked about we're talking about virtue
what what's the original meaning of
virtue well think about virtual reality
shaping of possibility virtue actually
means power
that's why we have phrases like in
virtue of right so
virtue actually means a power it means a
power to commit reliably
to what is good a power
to commit reliably to what is good
and so for aristotle what you do is you
build up things
that give that empower us at long
term habits and skills and then
you you have them directed towards
what is considered by you
in your most rational states the good
the true the good and the beautiful so
perhaps a better way of thinking about
it is right
is to say the stoics are
engaged in the psychology of trying to
examine
what actually keeps us committed
long term to the good and that is not
typically feeling that is typically
virtue
so hence wisdom because virtue
is just the way in which we are wise in
a particular situation
we bring sophia principle to bear
frognesis on a particular context so we
talked about this cultivation
of rationality in terms of the psycho
logic and this is me trying to remind
you that i'm not using logic
just in the modern sense this has to do
as i said not so much with argumentation
but much more with judgment and that
judgment has a lot to do with
this stoic practice pro soch
and prososh the best translation of
proshots is mindfulness so all the
mindfulness
training we did plugs in right here
right here
and so you don't typically think of
mindfulness as a logical
act but in terms of the logic of the
stoics mindfulness is a deeply logical
thing to do but a better way of putting
it
is that mindfulness is a deeply rational
thing to do think about
ra ra ratio and rationing
appropriately apportioning
and in proper proportion look at listen
how these words all sing together
appropriate you know proportioning and
proper
proportioning of your what you have your
affect
and what how you find things salient and
relevant that's the core
that's the core the core of this is
paying attention so your salience
landscape
shapes you towards
wisdom
so there's a triangle here and then
there
is ethics which doesn't mean what we've
reduced it to which is a very following
content very legal notion
of you know what's what's our duties and
what are the rules that we
have a duty towards for that for the
stoics this is again much more
psychological it's about how we deal
with impulse
we'll talk about that today and then
over here
we have physics and physics isn't
i mean it's not the same as modern
physics
what what we're doing here is learning
to discipline
desire so this
is learning to see things as they are
independent from the projections of our
desire
now of course modern physics tries to do
that too it tries to get us to see
things
objectively see them see see the thing
in terms of
just the properties that are belong to
the object
not things that we project on it in
terms of our values or our desires our
hopes
and so that's the connection here we're
trying to see things independent
of our projections we're trying to
withdraw our projections
here we're trying to do with that we're
trying to deal with that aspect of
ourself
that is not in our control the impulsive
aspect
okay
so this is all falls under the so the
two big things i said one was prososh
the other is prochyron
so prochyron is to practice so that
things become ready to hand
right so like so again the training of
habit
and skill and attention so things are
ready to hand
they come naturally to mind in the
situation
in which they are needed we're basically
trying to train how do we bring
principle
into process how do we make a process to
be governed by principle
and we've got we have to prac the thing
that link that here
okay principle
process and right what links them
practice again and again and again
again and again we oh we can all we love
to be
talking about our principles we also
like a pro oh just do what
feel go with your gut feel it just go
what you actually have to do according
to stoics is now you have to practice a
lot
getting clear about the principles and
bringing them into process
you have to practice to seeing what's
actually going on in the process
and putting it under the regulation of
the relevant
principles sophia from nieces
sophia fronesis
so i'm i'm the two books that we're most
relying on
right now um as you know
there's this book the one we're going
through the wisdom of hypatia
and then i'm especially making use of
this beautiful little gem of a book
by buzari stoic spiritual exercises
both books
[Music]
both books rely very highly on this book
by pierre hadeau
the inner citadel uh where pierre hadeau
talks about
uh the logic as the disciplining of
judgment or assent
the ethics as the disciplining of
impulse and
the physics is the disciplining of
desire
okay
[Music]
so bizarre talks a give some advice to
further refine the practice of
maximization
that we got from the epicureans the
creation of maxims
and trying and repeating them and sort
of making them permeate our lives
until um they come readily to hand
but she actually uh proposed she
actually proposes
a practice that i would using a term
from cognitive science involves deep
learning
so what she proposes you do is she
proposes
you read many different so here's read
in
many different instances of the
principle like marcus aurelius repeats
it
the principle epictetus repeats it
seneca repeats it
right read many different and then you
come up with your own right maxim
so this is a compression you try and
draw from all of them
what you think is most central about
them compressed to what is central
and then she recommends then practice
you from this
not from here but from yours create
variations on it
create variations rewrite it
play with it keep reworking it get
involved in a process of continually
rewriting continually recreating the
principle
this actually will help you to remember
it very very deeply
the way we get neural networks the
artificial intelligence that's so
powerful today is
we actually have them cycle through this
they take the data and they compress it
and then they do variation on it they
interact with the world then they
compress
it and they just keep cycling and that's
how you come to learn
something very very deeply so what she's
proposing this is my interpretation this
is my way of bringing some cogs eye into
it
she's proposing that don't just write
the maximizations
put them through a process of continual
deep learning
keep reading and compressing and then
creating variations and then recompress
from there
and keep refining it and recreating it
by the way this is the process
that makes you learn something hence the
name learn something very deeply and
make it very ready to hand
and actually internalize it so it starts
to become the very process
by which you're seeing the world it
becomes the lens through which you see
the world
okay
so you can put that of course into some
you can put that into relationship to
what
a practice we've already talked about
the self-examination at the end of the
day when you're journaling
you could also in addition to looking
for the your commission
right the advice you might have
committed a virtue you might have
omitted commission a mission the bias
remember
active open-mindedness and also the
virtue you might also want to practice
the deep learning of maximization the
deep learning
maximization uh uh the the the
slowly the stoic date prac the stoic
uh daily reading book that i recommended
to you by
was it ryan holiday is that right um uh
so you you can read it every day and he
has
a quote from one of the stoic
philosophers and then some exegesis on
it
and then you can go and look at similar
ones and you'll find the same practice
the same principles are being repeated
again and again and again
that's not because uh of kind of a just
a rote repetition they're trying to do
that process
you can see it in marcus releases
meditation of deep learning
deep learning of maximization
okay let's turn now to the core of the
psychologic what's the core of the
psychologic
the core of the psychologic is a
practice that bizarrey call
that calls pocket which means to bracket
or to suspend another way of thinking
about it
is to defuse and pull apart
things that are fused together in your
experience to reduce confusion
that way so the things that get fused
all together and are treated as one is
there's a thing
something in the world and then we get
what the stokes call an impression from
it
this is this is something over which
this is the part of the experience over
which we do not exercise
like there's just there's colors and the
shapes
and they're just right this is what's
happening automatically
in the sense of it's that part of your
perceptual system
that is that is most causally impacted
by the world
and not right the part that's affected
most directly by your judgment so
you get your initial impression and then
you
get and there's various ways of talking
about this you get you do
aspectualization
or you do categorization
you do conceptualization these are all
they're slightly different ways of
saying the same thing slightly different
conceptual conceptual
ization you actually create
propositional content sometimes this is
also called
representation it's how you present
something to it's been presented to you
here
in your senses and then you represent it
to your mind think about the word
representation means
you re-present it to your mind
so what this means is so you go from the
impressions to
let's try and do it slowly so here's an
impression
and then i start seeing it as a marker
and i categorize it as a marker that i
can use and knows how now i'm going in
it's an it and i'm going into the having
mode right away
and now i start to conceptualize it
things i can do with markers
and then i make some kind of
propositional
assertion about it uh this is a good
marker
or this marker is not so good because
it's running out of it i start to make
um a judgment about it
now like i said when all of this is
happening unconsciously
automatically and reactively mindlessly
then of course we are fettered to the
world
by all of this confusion
so what the stoics want us to do is they
want us to
introduce judgment here and i want to
use the greek word for judgment
because i think it's really helpful
crisis that's the greek word for
judgment
you go crisis crisis is a bad thing well
think about what we mean by a crisis
we mean things are being caught
everything that was
we thought was stable and secure that's
just the way it is
is actually being called into question
things are unraveling the structures are
coming
apart they're unraveling
and there's an opportunity for real
change
there's a critical moment crisis
critical cutting cross cutting across
these are all related ideas what we're
doing is trying to afford
the unraveling the coming apart the
calling into
question of this structure this fusion
so that we afford the possibility of
seeing
things differently we afford the
possibility of real
insight where we shift the aspect
we come to a new category we see new
possibilities
for how we can talk about it think about
it
reflect on it so this is actually
ultimately about trying to generate
insight
cognitive flexibility
now that this whole so
the they if you'll um this whole
sequence here
all of these things um epictetus calls
this
epilegene which this is from logos where
we get logic from
this we if this is related to our word
epilogue so the idea here is
this is all kind of inner speaking this
is speaking
after the impression the epilogue and
what we want to do
is we want to replace this automatic
epilogue
with critical dialogue we want to
replace the automatic
epilogue with critical dialogue we want
to
keep we want to pull it apart we want to
defuse it
so one way you can think about this is
ellen langer in his work
sorry in her work on mindfulness talks
about replacing
absolute learning with conditional and
she has
she has experimental evidence that this
really imperial improves people's
problem-solving ability
so if i were to teach you something
absolutely it would be this is what it
is
this is x when i teach it conditionally
i teach it to you
one way of thinking about this as as x
so i keep separate in how i'm teaching
it to you
all of this from the thing i don't fuse
them together and say
this is x what i do is say
one way of thinking about this is
x i replace epilogic
confusion and monologic reaction with
dial with critical dialogical
reflection
so i'm getting close to how
do you do this what's a way of doing
this
and so all three authors uh talk about
this pierre hadeau
and and uh you know a practice called
objective seeing
uh mcclellan in uh the wisdom of hypatia
calls it
neutral description uh bosari calls it
uh physical definition you can tell that
they're all trying to zero in
on something
and this has to go back to this notion
of ipake
which is suspending judgment by the way
and this
this is a valuable and hopefully useful
connection
this is a central practice within
the philosophical tradition known as
phenomenology
you try to right phenomena how things
are
shining how they're appearing to us and
you try
to get a very rigorous awareness of
how things are appearing to you and you
and and husserl who invented it
actually invented this process called
ipake
and if you want to get good at that
there's an excellent
really highly recommended book uh called
experimental phenomenology
by diane ivy where he takes you through
a whole bunch of exercises
what's valuable about this is it first
of all teaches you uh
how to do this kind of seeing or
description that we're talking about
it's actually how to do it right and
then
what's also valuable is that allows you
to make links
uh potentially between stoic philosophy
and continental philosophy people
talking about the meaning crisis
uh people like cultural and heidegger
etc so highly recommended
so what do we do with physical
definition
or i like to call it objective seeing
uh because i want to emphasize the
perceptual attentional aspect
buzzaro uh like i said uh bizarro
pizzari
calls it um physical description and
um the column calls it neutral
description so
how does it work well it's really
interesting because it actually plugs
into
a lot of the research on how you get
children to delay gratification
to and so uh and this is the famous
marshmallow test there's a confound in
the marshmallow test
with socioeconomic status having to do
long-term prediction
but you can put that aside you can look
at some of the mechanisms however
that do help people delay gratification
and one of them is this kind of
redescription
um there was a little girl so you put
you know the famous marshmallow you put
the marshmallow
in front and how long can they delay and
you say to them you you know
um you can eat the marshmallow whenever
you want the longer you wait though the
greater the chance will give you a
second marshmallow
and you measure how long they can delay
right until lane gratification is
important and what you
do it what one like what you do is you
get people to reframe it
uh one four-year-old did
she literally put a mental frame around
it and she treated it like a picture
of a marshmallow a representation
rather than the marshmallow itself
and she famously said well the way i
because you can't eat a picture
you can't eat a picture she pulled apart
the meaning
and the representation for her from the
thing itself
the marshmallow they also taught the
kids to zero in and redescribe
marshmallows as you know they're like
fluffy white clouds
so you you get a strategy of trying to
redescribe things re-ass spectralize
them re-categorize them
so that the the way they initially
present themselves to you falls into
crisis
in the sense of all of those things that
are fused together get pulled apart
and when you pull them apart that's the
space of your freedom
that's how you can see through those
cracks that you open up
that's that is the vehicle of insight
so what do we do
what do we do so let me give you an
example from marcus rillis and i chose
one that's a little off-putting
you go ich and that's and i chose it
deliberately for that reason
here's a quote from marcus aurelius
consider
sex as the friction of two pieces of
skin
and the ejaculation of a sticky fluid
and you go ew there what's wrong with
him
well what's he trying to do well
he's trying to describe it and that's
why uh bazaar calls it a physical
description
and the clone calls it a neutral
description he's trying to describe
the act the event from a purely
third person almost like the view from
above purely third person perspective
remember the research showing that if
you move from a first person perspective
to a third person perspective
you will also often get tremendous
insight into your problem
this is called the construal level
effect the solomon effect lots of
converging evidence on this
so he's trying to get you to describe it
from a non-human
perspective which is what physics tries
to do describe the world from a
non-human perspective
you're trying to strip it down to its
essence
the properties it would have even if
there were no human beings there
now obviously there has to be human
beings having sex but you know what you
know
what i'm trying to what i what i mean
here as if there were no human beings
uh there you try to take a non-human
perspective on it
you're trying to look at the whole to
break it analyze it into its whole
in parts what's its what it made of what
are the substances and
and the forces at work within it you're
trying to give it its most
proper name the name that would be true
in the greatest number of contexts that
description that marcus aurelius
made will be the case no matter what
kind of sex is happening
from the most horrible to the most
loving
and you go okay i get it why am i doing
that
because that is the practice by with
which you
train judgment by which you withdraw
projection
because when you do that when you're
doing the uk
what you're doing is you're realizing
that all of the beauty
has to do with what you're projecting
into the situation
and what that tells you is that maybe
it's not the sex
that is so valuable the sex per se
but all of that machinery uh by which
meaning is being made but maybe that in
fact
maybe that machinery could happen more
consciously more mindfully
and this of course is central to the
whole tradition of tantric sex
in which you realize wait what's
important
isn't the physical right what's
important is all of this that's built
around
it and i go from an absolute confused
meaning
to a conditional insightful meaning
of the event and
in that space metanoia
the changing of mind metanoia the word
we use for confu
for conversion shifting direction
metanoia
actually means to beyond how you're
beyond how you're noticing
a fundamental transcendence of your
salience landscaping
in that space of metanoia that's the
space in which i can
turn towards the good
i can aspire to wisdom
and virtue
so you can do objective seeing
neutral description physical description
throughout your day
you can actually also do it as you know
at the end of a sit at practice you can
open your eyes
and look at an object that you have
a strong relationship to now sometimes
some stoics recommend start with objects
that are actually you're almost neutral
towards because it's easier
to give a neutral description of them
and then go
by degrees like progressive
desensitization
to redescribing things that are less
neutral to you
but in an increasingly like you'll sense
it as an increasingly
more neutral fashion and by that
progressive
movement you will learn to
be happy more critical in your judgment
and you'll be there by training your
psychologic
so what we're going to continue to do is
we're going to take a look at each one
of these
right the logic the physics and the
ethics and look about the
the particular spiritual exercises you
can do for each one of these
as a way of training irrationality
cultivating
uh virtue and aspiring to wisdom okay so
i'm going to go back
on to the cushion nose so i can see the
questions
and uh take any questions that people uh
might have
about today's dharma or about last time
with the view from above
or anything from the wisdom of hypatia
or in fact anything from the
entire meditation and cultivation of
wisdom series
so the first question is from pleasure
of doubt or brett
uh brad i haven't talked to you in a bit
i miss talking to you again i will see
you monday night though because
i'll be on the discord server for the
monthly q a
uh x the the question brad asks is i
think is like a crucial question here
does internalizing socrates require
having deeply studied properties
to it to a significant degree yes so
um it used to be
people of course we had a wisdom
tradition
in which people always had at least one
sage that they had internalized
for many people for example it might be
jesus or
moses or or muhammad
right um but we've we've lost that
uh we all walk around
that's too strong i'm sorry many of us
walk around with a hole in our heart
that we don't even realize that we have
and it's a place
but that is ready for the reception of
the internalized sage
i actually think given the situation we
in that we should have a community of
sages that we've internalized
so i try to internalize uh socrates um
platinus uh spinoza siddhartha
and jesus of nazareth
so i think it's important to uh
learn about socrates and one of the
great gifts given to us and we'll talk
about this when we move into
uh the third degree of wisdom is the
platonic dialogues they're not always
easy
and i recommend starting with the more
popular ones like the symposium
or the republic or listening to them on
audiobook which is very helpful for many
people
because they're actually dialogues and
the point of a dialogue is not just what
people say
the point is also because that's only
propositional the point is the drama
the perspectival right the perspectives
that are there
and the participatory knowing the
character that are there
and so reading and learning more of just
familiarizing yourself with socrates in
the situation of socratic dialogue
definitely helps there's lots of
excellent books and if people want i
could recommend some books to read
to get a sense of it there's lots of
videos on this
um there i think it's the fourth episode
of my video series
awakening from the meeting crisis helps
so what you want to do is
you're not so much trying to
get um some sort of
philosophical scholastic historically
accurate thing
i mean that's an that's a goal that you
can have but the goal
here is to get something that is
reliably going to work to help you
do the stoic practices and then so hello
calls this the figure of socrates
the figure of socrates so you want to
practice
configuring socrates and figuring him
out
if you'll allow me to play a little bit
with words and so
um i'm going to do something to help
people address this and it's been
something that
has had that has been put off
because of funding circumstances and
covid but also it's turned around to be
a fantastic opportunity
i'm putting together another series that
is going to be at the level of
awakening from the meaning crisis which
is called after socrates
and the cultivation of wisdom and virtue
and so
that will help people with this i hope
uh deborah wagstaff so children learn to
pay attention to how they pay attention
by imitating the
adults around them doing the same that's
exactly right
so this is called natural pedagogy
natural pedagogy
that most of how we learn to see the
world
which is also a process by which we are
enculturated
into a particular community is through
imitation and internalization
of how other people see the world that's
why you know this is a really good
proverb
children don't pay attention to what you
say they pay attention to what you do
you can say the most beautiful things
but it's actually what you do
that really matters that's why we even
have this phrase it's a really good
phrase
in deed think about what the word means
if you say
that that that that is the case indeed
we mean
in action in action is where it really
happens
so uh deborah wagstaff i was slowly
coming back
i reached out to touch saturn as i
passed suddenly realizing i was massive
expanded to hold saturn if i wished
focusing on maintaining expansion and
filling my body so i i believe that
deborah was talking about last week
and she was talking about the view from
above and yeah so
your your sense of self and your
identity will become
like wisdom-filled water or even
wondered phil
wonderful wonder filled i was going to
say wonderful but this is better
wonder filled water you'll feel your
identity moving around in
the state of wonder because wonder is
exactly the state in which we are
calling ourselves
and how we see things into question and
so you get that wondered filled
watery sense of self it flows it expands
it shifts
it moves and what that does is challenge
again the automaticity by which we
assume
and assign identities so thank you for
that
manual post great to see you emanuel
uh the lesson is focused on the
depersonalization of things i'm
wondering if there's a set of practices
that does the opposite um so
it's not so much it's depersonalizing um
not for its own sake uh it's crisis
your your so the point is to
introduce enough depersonalization so
that you don't have absolute learning
you still have conditional learning
you're not going to stop seeing persons
as persons
because in fact that's a proper name for
this particular kind of individual
so what you might be saying is well i
will see things a lot less
anthropomorphically
um and so within sourcism manual you're
not going to see
something that counterbalances that but
within neoplatonism
you'll see you'll see something that
counterbalances that which is
after people have gone through rigorous
rational training
so they're not doing anthropomorphic
projection
then you can bring back a symbolic way
of seeing things as a way of cultivating
wisdom but the point
of the neoplatonus is if people do the
second
without having deeply done the first the
chance that they are going to fall into
unrecognized projection
and thereby significant self-deception
is very very high
um and so that's why it's a a lot of
these wisdom traditions converge
and even in the buddhism remember the
famous quote from the buddha this is how
you'll know
somebody is not my disciple if they
offer to perform a miracle
right so the the uh the idea of
you know magical projection is is
always called very deeply into question
by all these traditions
uh because of the proclivity uh for
uh self-deceptive projection within it
so in answer to your question
not so much within stoicism not so much
within high school but once you've done
the high school
you move into university neoplatonism
and neoplatonism has
theorgic practices that do exactly what
you're asking me about
but they do it on the understanding that
you have passed through
uh elementary and uh elementary school
in high school so i hope that answers
your question
uh robert gray follow up to brett's
question does internalizing someone
alive differ widely from someone you've
only read about or heard about second
hand
the christ or buddha like a mentor
parent friend
um so i think i've met people who
whose sage is someone living and they've
internalized
um the difficulty there
the difficulty there is um when we have
a personal relation
well think about how elevated the buddha
and christ are
for many people and if you push if you
project
that elevated status onto a human being
the buddha and christ have passed into
mythos
and i don't mean that in a pejorative
sense and that again
alludes to what manual was talking about
they've passed into mythos
and so it is not unbearable for them to
have
that kind of elevated status but
treating a living human being
with that elevated expectation can be
very crushing and demanding on them
and it can and they can they they can
suffer the fate of icarus
um under our hands um and you know that
there's a famous song by ziggy
by david bowie stardust about how the
fans actually destroyed ziggy
because they elevated him into a leper
messiah
um and so yes you can
but you have to remember to
counterbalance that with not
dehumanizing the person we forget that
there are two ways of dehumanizing
somebody
and this was something that conrad's
literature is so good on we can
dehumanize people
by right treating them
by demonizing them right and that's
something we're very concerned with
rightly so by the way
in our culture right now but what we
don't pay enough attention critical
critical crisis attention to is how you
can de-personalize somebody by deifying
them
and that's just as disastrous that's the
problem of colonel kurtz
right in the heart of darkness so
if you can have a stereoscopic vision of
the living person if you can through one
eye
see them mythologically as the sage
but through the other eye see them in a
way
that maintains their meant their their
humanity
that is the golden mean between
demonizing them and deifying them
then a living person can be internalized
as a sage griswold grim
how much difference between an
internalized socrates and socrates
daemon so that's a really good question
and the stoics talk about that inner
part of themselves as the ruling faculty
they sometimes talked about it as the
internal sage they often
often call that their daemon uh and what
uh what
griswold is referring to is that
socrates had
daemon isn't the same thing as demon
demon is another thing in which we've
degraded a term
to give it exactly the opposite meaning
damon was the voice from a higher order
perspective than your own
ego perspective identity when you get
like for
the equivalent in the in the um eastern
tradition
is the buddha within the buddha within
that's your damon
peter lindberg talks about uh how his
damon leads us
right it's it's your sacred second self
your divine double
it's the voice of the third person
perspective that is calling you vocation
calling you to the good calling you to
wisdom um and socrates had such a voice
it would it would when he when he was
about to do something wrong
and it's not just conscience that's
trivialized when he was about to do
something wrong it would impact on him
and his whole he would be turned
metanoia away from
uh on that and so i think for the stoics
and especially for modern stoics like
peter lindberg internalizing socrates
and cultivating a socratic daemon
something that
uh um emulates and imitates socrates
damon they're one in the same process
they're two different ways of talking
about the same thing and it's a very
powerful so of course people
um uh often also uh christians
experience the voice of christ
the voice of jesus or or the moving of
the holy spirit
um and of course the buddha the
buddhists have the buddha nature
um interestingly in taoism it's much
more impersonal but you you
you feel the dao and you feel that that
often is
key or chi um redirecting what you find
salient
and the identities you're assuming and
assigning
thinking of chia's secret magical energy
is
such a profound and almost
racist misreading of that concept
it's such a bad misappropriation
of that concept uh jensen kim and i are
actually
writing a paper to really try and
recapture
uh the ecologically valid meaning of qi
within taoism
and how that can actually be integrated
very uh
i think very insightfully not trying to
be self-congratulated but that's the
wrong way then
but very significantly like it will have
it fits together well that's what i'm
trying to say sorry it sounds
self-congratulatory
but a way of reinterpreting
in an ecologically valid way the notion
of chi or key
that fits in plugs in really well
to uh current cognitive science so that
we don't need to think of it
like and it shouldn't be thought of
because this is again a western category
as a supernatural substance or as a um
as some kind of ethereal ectoplasmic
force or all the guish
silliness that people have done um in
their misunderstanding
of that so um in the dallas tradition
your demon is is much more the
experience of
chi or ki okay so that's a lot
so thank you so much uh everyone for
joining
this the saturday sanghas i look forward
to them
so much thank you to amara jason